晚上好
Good evening.
我想打个电话到意大利
1d like to call Italy.
好的
Very wel.
请您写一下号码
You may dial the number.
喂 委得罗 我是埃茉娜
Hello? Pietro, it's Elena.
两个孩子怎么样了 跟你有什么关系
How are the girls? What do you care?
她们是我的女儿
They're my daughters.
你想要干什么
What do you want?
丙泰尔的出版社想在巴黎再办一些推介会
The French publishers want to do more promotional events in Paris.
我应该会答应她们
1thought 1d accept.
但无论如何我都会在平安夜回到家
|川| be back for Christmas Eve.
这已经是本月你第二次去法国了
Youve already gone to France twice in two months
从你决定毁挥我们这个家庭以来
Since you decided to destroy our family.
你不回来也无所谓
Don't bother to come back.
在我和尼诡逃离到法国的那几个月里
In those months, during my escapes to France with Nino,
呈|
我脑子里一直想着售售和艾尔沙
Dede and Elsa came to mind constantly,
也想着役得罗
as did Pietro，
但他们束好像生活在一个平行世界里
but as if suspended in a parallel universe.
我有好几天没听到她们的消息了
1d had no news of them for some days,
而随着我意识到这一点 我感到一阵强烈的肪时
and as |became aware of that | felt an intense nausea
但纵使这多么难以忍受
But as unbearable as it was，
我不能拒绝那两位女编辑的邀请
1couldnt turn down the invitation from the two publishers
她们那么信赖我的新书
who had believed in the book
我推迟几天回家 也不会改变什么
Putting off my return for a few days wouldn't change much.
还是这 我一切都做错了
Or was | getting everything wrong?
我不能打太久电话 我们过几天再说吧
1 cant stay on the phone. Let's talk soon.
不 这我没法跟你襄
No, | cant tell you that.
尼诡 再见
Nino.
对不起 我没听到你敲门
Sorry, 1 人 hear you.
你在给埃利奥话拉打电话吗
Were you on the phone with Eleonora?
Absolutely not.
是真的 你残是个骗子
It's the truth1You're a liar.
我友冰 是乌特勒文那个无聊的教授
1 swear 让was that boring professor from Utrecht.
我觉得他是喝多了 他说的一句话我都没听懂
|think he was drunk, too. | couldnt understand a word.
你融是在和埃利奥话拉打电话 我听到了
You were talking to Eleonora, | heard you.
你不可能听到 因为事实不是这样
You can't have heard me, because it's not true.
你相信我吗
Do you believe me?
尔得信任我
You have to trust me.
我是这样想 的
This is what | think:
虽然我们的处境很复杂
our Situation is complicated，
但我们会解决的
but we'l sort it out.
不过我们不能一直逃避
But to do that we cant keep running away，
蒙役利埃 巴黎 不知道还要逃到哪个城市
Montpellier Paris, then who knows what other city!
我们得面对这个局面
We have to face this situation head-on.
我和埃利奥话拉 你和你的丈夫
Me, Eleonora. And you, your husband.
你今晚美极了
You were stunning tonight.
整个晚上我的眼睛都没离开过你 真的吗
| had my eyes on you the whole time. Yes?
而且不止我这样
And 1wasnt the only one.
睡吧
Go to sleep.
佛罗伦联火车站
你打算再也不跟我说话了吗
Not talking to me now?
至少告诉我为什么吧 打给我
At least tell me why. Call me.
你不接我电话吗
You're not picking up?
你是在生我的气吗
Are you offended with me?
你会回那不勒斯过圣诞吗
You coming to Naples for Christmas?
还是我 莉拉 我现在对你有操生气了
This is Lila, again. You're getting on my nervesl
我给你打了一个月的电话 你到搬在干什么
lve been calling you for a month. What are you playing at?
喂 马丽姬罗沙 是
Hello? Mariarosa, it's me.
皮生什么了 我不知道 你来告诉我 家里一个人都没有
Whats up? You tell me, there's no one home.
几点 了三   三点
Whattme is it? lt's 3:00 a.m.
你这个点才回来 对 友生了什么
产浊 just got back now? Yes, what's going on?
孩子们还好吗 当然 你冷静一操
Are the girls all right? Yes, calm down.
她们很好 在都灵和我父母在一起
They're fine, they're in Turin with my parents.
航得罗之前和我说 她们等我回来 一起吧圣诞晚餐
Pietro told me they were expecting me for Christmas dinner.
结果他把她们市去了都灵
But he took them to Turin.
不 是我母亲来接走了她们
No, my mother came and picked them up.
也不通知我一声吗 她怎么能这样
Without telling me? How dare she?
她想着或许最好让你和彼得罗独处
She thought ii was better to leave you and Pietro alone
这样万便处理你们之间的事情
to deal with the Situation freely.
她想着 这可不是她能做主的事
She thought? She doesn't decidel
凑晨三点了 你现在才到家
You got back at three in the morning，
这算哪门子的圣诞节
what kinda lousy Christmas would it have been?
是的 因为过节路上了拉了
There were delays because of the holidays.
你不需要辩解 我没有在辩解
No need to justify yourself. rm notl
埃莱娜 你有权利也有义务 持续学习 写作
You have the right and the duty to keep studying, writing.
其余的 我给不了你任何建议
As for the rest | cant give you any advice.
别乐了米兰这边的新书友表会啊
Dont forget ab about the presentation here in Milan.
你的老朋友弗明科也会到场 他授不及竺想见到你
The great Franco Mari will be there too, he cant wait to see you.
好 好
Yes', yesS，
那么 晚安
Wel goodnight.
你去哪儿了
Where have you been?
你能不能告诉我 为什么让你母亲带走孩子们
Why did you let your mother take the girls?
你听得见我在说什么吗
Did you hear me?
你当时在法国工作
You were in France, for work.
如果不是火车晚点 我本可以及时回来的
ld have made itin time, but the trains were |ate.
但事实是对女儿们来六 你一直都不在
Youre never here for your daughters.
彼得罗 我们谈谈吧
Pietro, let's talk.
我们要找到一个解决方案
We need to reach an agreement.
两个孩子要和我一起生活
The girls will come live with me,
你周末可以和她们见面
you'l see them on weekends.
在哪里见面
川| see them, where?
企我家里
At my house.
你家在哪里
And where's that?
我不知着 我会决定好的
| dont know, 川| decide.
这里
Here
米三 或者那不勒斯
in Milan, in Naples.
那不勒斯吗 那不勒斯
In Naples?
我永远不会允许 我的文儿和你生活在那不勒斯
川 never let my daughters live with you in Naplesl
你介吗 我永远不会同意
川 never accept thatl
航得罗 你冷静一操
Calm down.
Yv人人主名_    Zrh ZX电
/评卓    误 彼得
Calm down, Pietro.
我这样惑没法开车了
| candt drive |ike thiSs.
你要去哪儿 去火车站
Where do you need to goy? To the train station.
云干电
What for?
去接你母亲
To pick up your mother.
My mother?
忠得有人告诉她 你对我所做的一切 那是我的事
Someone had to tell her. 此was up to mel
你会对她撤汶 融如同你对我所做的一般
You would have lied like you did to me.
你们看 很简单的
Seey It's easy.
你们俩是天生一对 都爱看书学习
Youre made for each other you like reading, studying.
你们都很取明
You're clever
但如果一遇到困难惑放弃 这叫什么取明
But what good is it ifyou give up when it gets hard?
你们得考虑考虑孩子
Think of the kidS.
信介已经长大了 让她受罪真是太不应该了
Dede's big now and its not right to make her suffer.
航得罗 我感谢你为我女儿所做的一切
Pietro, thank you for everything youve done for my daughter，
但是你不原谅她 我融不会离开
but lm not leaving until you forgive her.
我以佩佩 詹尼和埃莉沙的性何友壮 你们不和好 我融不回家
| swear on my kids' lives lm not leaving until you make upl
来吧 给彼此一个吻吧
Give each other a kisS.
茉农 道歉 说你销了 仑求你浆夫的原谅吧
Lenu, say you're sorry and admit you were wrong.
Lenu, come 落人
妈妈 够了
Cutitoutl
没用的 我受上别人了
There's no point. 1 love someone else.
闭噶 你这个嫩子
Shut up, you slutl
我再也忍受不了你了
| canttake ii with you anymorel
你介吗 我受不了你
1 canttake it anymorel
项为了那个男的 你想毁反目己的生活
You 由 ruin your life chasing after a man
他比他父杀那个王八量更糟糕
who's a bigger shit than his shitty fathenl
以前我以为是你朋友者娜把你市十了
|thought it was Lila leading you down the wrong path,
但我错了 你才是那个不要脸的
but 1 was wrong, you're the shameless hussyl
你这个不要脸的寻子
You're a shameless hussyl
没有你 莉娜现在成了一个正经的好女人
Without you，Lila's become a good person.
我真该在你小时候打断你的腿
| shoulda broke your legs when you were little!
你有这样一个完美的浆夫
Your husband's worth his weight in goldl
让你生活在这么漂亮的房子里
He has you live in a beautiful housel
他和你生了两个女儿
He gave you two kidsl
你融是这样报答他的吗 混账东西
And this is how you repay him? Cowl
过来 我要打有死你
Im gonna kill youl
9Stop it
你不是我的女儿了
You're not my daughter anymore.
他才 是我| U子
我希望萨拉托雷的儿子 让你染上淋病和梅毒
| hope Sarratore's son gives you the clap and syphilis!
我到帮做了什么蕊 才看到这一天啊
What did 1do wrong to live to see this day?
是我活该吗
Did | deserve this?
上帝啊 让我死吧
Lord, take me nowl
如果上和可怜我 融让我立刻死挥吧
Take me nowl
不用开门
Don't open the door.
我不是想进来
hm not asking you to let me in.
我只是想告诉你 我也不希望这样
ljust want to say | didn't want this.
这有些过分了
It's too much _.
你不应该受到这样的对街
Not even you deserve it.
我为目己推她的方式感到郑愧
| was ashamed of how | shoved her
我为她也为目己感到着愧
| was ashamed of her and of myself.
我本想要章灼 拥抱她
| wanted to apologize, to hug her.
但我怕这样 会让她认为我让步了
But | feared she'd be convinced 1d given in.
我们没再说一句话 她残走了
She left without us speaking a word to each other.
她祝役得罗一切都好
She wished Pietro all the best
一直叮嘱他 直到火车出发前一刻
and urged him, until a moment before the train left,
说要随时告知她 他手上的伤 以及孩子们的消息
to keep her informed about his wounded hand and about the girls.
Hello?
你好 阿售尔
Hi Adele.
明天我要去接我的廊儿们
Im coming to pick up my daughters tomorrow.
埃茉娜 真是尺训 圣诞快乐
Elena, what a surprise. Merry Christmas.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
埃莱娜 你别担心
Dont worry，
你希望她们留在这里多久都可以 放完假之后也
you can leave them with me for as long as you need.…
袋售需要上学
Dede has School|.
如果你需要时间 集合可以在这里上学 这附近有一个
9he could go to school here, there's one nearby.…
不行 我必须把她们市在身边
No, | need to keep them with me.
我拜托你 仔细想想这件事
Please, just think about 六.
单亲妈妈 两个女儿和你的野心
Aseparated woman with two daughters and your ambitions
你应该看清现实
has to face reality
台
要想清楚 要保留什么 放弃什么
乞 decide what to give up.
明天见
1 see you tomorrow.
明天你不是要去米三见玛丽娅罗沙吗
Arent you supposed to be in Milan with Mariarosa tomorrow?
那融周五吧 我坐第一班火车
Itake the first train on Friday, then.
贱人
Bitchl
我出生在一个贫穷 破落的街区
| was born in a poor run-down neighborhood，
非营破落
very run-down.
在那里 男人们的屈怒和暴力
Where men's fury, their violence,
从始至终都是家弟便饭
was and is a daily occurrence.
十多的时候 我见过一个父亲把女儿扔出窗外
lve seen a father throw his daughter out the window
就因为她想继续上学
only because she wanted to keep studying.
我见过一个女人上吊目杀
lve seen a woman hang herself
因为她成了熹妇 有两个孩子要抚养
because she was widowed with two children to support.
我见过一个朋友脸上的猴伤
lve Seen bruises on a friend's face
因为她嫁给了不爱的男人
because she'd married a man she didnt |ove.
这个男人在新婚之夜盟奸了她
A man who raped her on her wedding night.
那你呢
And you?
你的镑又是什么呢
What are you guilty of?
是离开 离开所有这一切吗
Of going away, of leaving everything?
是学习男人的语言 局
Of learning the language of males
来使你的书更加成功吗
to have more Success with your books?
我钦佩挨琳娜 正是因为她的男性气质
1admire Elena precisely because of her masculine capacities.
我坚持认为 她一直在磨练这种气质
And | insist she keeps honing them
并没有迷失在女性的义务中
without losing herself in women's obligations.
谢谢
Thanks.
你用手头拥有的东西 在尽可能地进行着革命 不是吗
You make revolution with what's at hand, dont you?
已经不再有人想半命
No one wants revolution anymore.
我不同意 西尔维亚
| wouldn't say that, Silvia.
但她襄得有道理
She's right though.
持合季节正随着
The 本 Season is fading，
所有5|导它的事物 逐渐消失
along with all the categories that guided it.
米尔区 埃斯特 去吧垂品吧
Mirko, Ester dessertl
抱歉 弗明科 不是这样的
Franco, its not |ike that.
生意大利一切都很活跃 充满了斗争精神
In ltaly the Situation is very lively and combative.
你这么说 是因为你活涛好斗
You say that because you're lively and combative.
你对目己很满意
You're pleased with yourself.
恰恰相反 我很抑郁
Not at all, |"m depressed.
消沉的人才不写书呢
Depressed people don't write books.
只有开心的人会写书
Books are written by people who are happy,
到处旅行恋爱的人
who travel, who fallin love
这些人确信 三 己说的话  总会派上用场
and speak with the conviction that words will fall into place.
不用面对任何挑战 当然是很舒适的
Its comfortable not being challenged by anything.
没有任何感染的伤口
No wound to get infected，
缝合的地方也没有留下伤疤
no cut that needs stitches，
没有令人害怕的暗室
no dark room that scares you.
最后 这个佼俩融不管用了
In the end, the trick stops working.
什么意思
MAN
Meaning?
轨明叫 埃茉娜
Blah, blah, blah, Elena.
意义已经脱离语言
Words are losing their meaning.
有电话 找你的
lts for you.
是谁
Who is it?
尼话
Nino.
Hello?
嗨
Hi Hi，
上友生什么了吗
Has Something happened?
是的 我想你想得快疯掉了
Yeah, | miss you like crazy.
我想到了一个好主意 既然我们有几天空末时间
Seeing as we have Some free time,，
为什么不去海边呢
why dont we go to the seaside?
我们在中间找个地万见吧 在阿根塔里奥 融我们俩
Let's meet halfway, at Argentario, just you and |.
你和你妈妈之间友生了那些事 我觉得休息一下 对你有好处
After what happened with your mothenr a break will do you good.
什么时候去呢
But when?
我想着明天 最晚后天
Tomorrow or the day after at the latest.
我得去都灵接女儿们 我去不了
|haveto goto Turin to pick up the girls, 1 cantt.
大学的课很快要开始了 之后我融很难走开了
川 be busy soon at the university, it pe hard for me to get away.
别 我知道
Te
我真不知道该怎么办
| don't know what to do.
唤两天 有什么关系
lts just two days, what's the big deal?
你不再;  想念我了 吗
Dont you miss me anymore?
你不再需要我了吗
Dont you need me anymore?
你在开玩笑吗
You kidding me?
我等不及要抱你了 真的吗
1 cant wait to hold you again. You sure?
真的
我不确定 你似乎有很多事情要民
You seem so taken up by your things.
尼庄 你错了
Nino, you're wrong.
再说一志
9ay it again.
你销了
You're wrong.
那个周五 我没有去接女儿们
That Friday, 1 didn't go back for the girls
阿售尔一点都不惊订
and Adele didn't seem at all surprised.
我意识到我的效婆提出了一个真正的问题
realized my mother-in-law had raised a real problem，
我如何在女儿们和尼诡之间 平衡我的生活
how could 1 keep my life with Nino and my daughters together?
罗马中央火车站
残这样 我决定把女儿们托付给阿复尔
And so, | decided to entrust my daughters to Adele.
只要我一有空 我融会回去看她们
| went to visit them whenever | could .
和尼诺在一起时 我想见她们
When lspent time with Nino 1 wanted to be with them，
和入全 艾尔沙在一起时 我却想见
and when | was with Dede and Elsa | wanted to be with 见尼
那些年我们的生活 一直都没有安定过
In those years Nino and | were always on the move.
我们想出面参与 观察 研究
We wanted to be present, to observe, to Study,
去理解 分析 作证
to understand, to reason, to bear witness
尤其是 去相爱
and above all to love each other.
警察无情的鸣笛 检查站
The wailing police sirens, the roadblocks,
直升机螺旋桨的呼啸户 被红色旅杀害的人
the whir of helicopter blades, people killed by the Red Brigades，
都是我们在一起的时间线上的标坊
marked this chapter of our relationship.
几个星期 几个月
Weeks months，
第一年 伏后是一年半
ayear and then ayear and a half
这一切的一切 都是从佛罗伦萨的那个夜里
every public event took on meaning only from that night
我进到尼诡的房间 开始算起
at my house in Florence when |joined Nino in his room.
我们襄从那时候起 生活才刚刚开始
That was when, we told each other our true life had begun.
我们称之为真正的生活
And what we called true life
即使每天面对可怕的场景
was that sense of miraculous splendor that never left us
那种神奇的感觉也没有散去
not even when everyday horrors played out around us.
早上好 基督教民主兑的领字 莫罗
Moro, leader of the Christian Democratic party
今早9点10分遭遇恐怖分子绑织
was kidnapped this morning by a squad of terrorists.…
各位同僚 我认为正是在这样的赤剧时刻
Colleagues, precisely in this dramatic moment,
我们必须理智地诚实地提醒自己
we must have the intellectual honesty to remind ourselves
那个给国家抹黑
that the one who threw mud on the state，
暴露出国家最糟糕一面的人
Who revealed its worst face，
那个为红色旅诞生创造了条件的人
and who also created the conditions for the birth of the Red Brigades.
考虑到他目前所处的情况 我很抱歉这么襄
|m sorry to Say this given the Situation he's in，
但那个人恰恰融是莫罗
but 由was Morao
他蔡腐败的政党 隐满那些令人不安的真相
Concealing uncomfortable truths for his corrupt party.
甚至把目己的政党 等同于国家
Indeed, identifying the party with the state itself
你在说什么 意思是 这一切是莫罗各由目取吗
What are you Saying, that Moro's guilty?
打住 别评陷我 说我没说过的话
No, don't make me say things 1 didn't say.
我是况 我们必须持卫国家机构
1 Say we must defend the institutions
但择卫并不意味着掩善他们的罪行 而是使一切公开透明
not by hiding their misdeeds, but by making them transparent，
不回避任何事情
With no omissions.
你是站哪边的
What side are you on?
我一定要选边站吗 那我站我的理智这边 可以吗
Im on the side of my head.
不好意思 现在不是讨论这些的时间
This isntthetime for discussions of this kind.
那残别开会了
Then let's not hold conferences
因为总会有其他更紧急的事
because there'l always be another emergency.
只有莫罗理解我们这个时代的解放进程
Only Moro has understood the processes of liberation of our time.
他认可青年和女性运动的力量
He recognized the strength of the youth and feminist movements，
而那些左派则任由我们目生目次
While even the Left abandoned usSl
有谁反对了这一点吗 您说了
And who said the contrary? 昌
没有的事 我认同你的说法
Not at all, | agree with you.
您对这样一个处于生命危险中的人 曼无同情 真是可下
You're being CH about a man whose life is in dangernl
不 我比你更同情他
No, | have more pity than you.
同情意味着看到现实 然后去感类它
Pietas means to see reality and then to sense it.
我可以走 没问题
1 can leave, no problem.
你霸么敢说这种话
How dare you Say these thingSs?
你两个月前说了同样的话
You were Saying 月 Same things two months ago.
你搞错了 那不是我
You're mistaken, that wasnt me.
你摘混了 你记性太差了
You're getting it mixed up! You have a short memory.
继续你们的研讨会吧
Go ahead with your conference.
但请别张嘴闭嘴 融是萨尔维米尼
But dont f仙 your mouths with Gaetano 9alvemini.
先去读读他的书吧
Read him first.
无聊得要死 伪善小人的聚会
Deadly boring, the festival of hypocrisy!
你是站哪边的   有意 意思吧
"What side are you on?" Did you like it?
只有我们最重要
Only we mattered
只要我们俩是一心的残够了
and every time it converged back to the two of us.
假如我们在一起 融没有任何批评能伤害到我们
上 we were together no criticism could touch us.
我们反倒会变得很骄做
On the contrary we became conceited，
我们的观点是最重要的 其他事情都没有意义
nothing made sense except our opinions.
我们一起去吃饭 享受美食 红酒和性爱
Weranto dinners, to good food, to wine', to sex.
我们只想紧紧拥抱在一起
All we wanted was to hold each other cling to each other
我有一件事要告诉你
| have something to tell you.
看你脸色应该挺严肃的
From the look on your face it seems serious.
这是我这奉子做过的最着耻的一件事
Its perhaps the most shameful thing lve ever done in my life.
是关于我高中委托你写的文章
Its about the article | commissioned from you at high school.
你吓我一跳
You Sscared me.
你在说什么
What are you talking about?
关于你和军教老师友生冲突的事情 你记得
The story about the clash with the religion teacher.
你做了什么
What did you do?
当时读的时候
When | read 让
我党得那篇文章看起来很舒服 而且殉满智慧
| couldn't believe someone could write in a way
我总得不可思议
that was So pleasing and intelligent.
我改了很多次
| rewrote it so many times.
我长至去找了莉拉 让她帮有我修改
| even asked Lila to read it and help me.
我想在你面前好好表现一下
| wanted to impress you.
后来他们没有友表那篇文章 我还很伤心呢
| was upset that they didn't publish it
我当时跟你说 是因为版面不够了 对吗
| told you it was for lack of space, right?
是的
Yes, |think So.
事实上 当时有足够的版面友表你那篇文章
The truth is there was plenty of space.
那他们为什么不出版它
Then why didn'tthey publish it?
出于嫉妨
Out of envy.
那些编辑立妒我吗
The editors were envious of me?
是我人妨你
| was the one who was enviousS.
我看了你的文章 然后把它们扔进了垃圾桶
read your pages and lthrew them in the garbage,
没法容忍你写得那么好
| couldn't bear that you were So good.
他没有必要告诉我那件事
There was no need to tell me about that episode,
但他说了
and yet he did.
他对真诚的重视 超越了任何利益考量 这让我很感动
His need to be sincere beyond any bene代 moved me.
从那一时刻起 突然之间
From that moment on，
我觉得我可以一直相信他
felt 1 could always believe him
我可以信赖我心中正在滋生的那个想法
And | could trust the idea that was growing inside me，
和他有一个家
to get a house together
将我们的生活和我的女儿们联结起来
and finally unite our life with my daughters.
我爱你
| love you.
我也爱你 你知道吗
1love you too, you know?
我也有一件事情要告诉你
| have Something to tell you, too.
告诉我
Tell me.
Maybe it's just ie
但是呢
But ?
余斩、
会是谁
Who's that?
谁知道我们在这几
Who knows we're here?
只有阿售尔
Only Adele.
接电话吧
AnSswer .
Hello?
役得罗
Pietrol
埃茉娜
Elena_.
你怎么样
How are you?
情况本来可能更糖糙
lt could have been WwWorse.
这是埃莱娜 这是多莉姬娜
Elena, this is Doriana.
你好 你好
Hello._ Hello.
皮生了什么
How did it happen?
我不六记得了
1dont remember very wel，
两个人拿着棍子朝我过来 给我来了这么一下子
two guys came at me with a stick and then a massive blow.…
我觉得我景倒了
| think | fainted .
他们是谁 法西斯 暴徒
Who were they? Fascists, violent guysS.
疼吗
Does it hurt?
我不知着这里面有什么 但我感觉比以往任何时候都更好
| dont know what's in here but lve_ never felt better
医生说你得多喝水 好
The doctor said you have to drink.
How are you?
你最近霸么样
挺好的
瓯是有点累
Alittle tired .
还是一直在出差吗 是的
Still traveling? Yes.
爸爸 你还好吗
Papal Are you all right?
慢点 他不能到
Easy, he cant move.
你还疼吗
Does it Still hurt?
你好 多莉娅娜
Good morning, Doriana.
你香么样 我很好
How are you? Fine.
埃茉娜 你到得真快
Elena, you got here quickly.
是的 我赶了第一班火车
Yes, |took the first train.
笋售 广尔沙 向妈妈问好呀
Dede, Elsa, say hello to Mamma.
你好 妈妈 你好
Hi Mamma. Hi.
你好啊 集合
Hi Dede.
你们都长大了
Youve grown.
你们都长这么大了
Youve grown So much.
区
苑 我语文成绩拿了A 太棒了
Papa,1got an Ain ltalian. Well donel
老师襄我本来可以拿A+ 但是我跑题了
| could have gotten an A+, but 1 went off topic.
没关系的
lts all right.
我给你做了一件礼物 真的吗
| made           ent. Really?
奶奶 我的礼物呢
andma, wher
哎呀 对不起 宝贝
Darling, |m sorry，
我应该是扎在家里了
|think we left it at home.
不可能吧 我伦了好几天做的
|dont believe 册 it took me days to makel
这是专门给多区的
此was special for Papal
别担心 明天再给他吧
Never mind, give it to him tomorrow.
小军贝
Darling.
谁起和我去买荞条
Who's coming with me to get 条叶
Me. Me, but 1 站 和] Ce 同
可以吗
May |?
可以 但是你们要每人吧一半
All right but you have to share it.
我也款 我需要来怀咖味
1 go too
坐下吧
Sit down .
她很不销
She's very nice.
你爱她吗
Are you in love?
我已经很久没这么开心过了
| havent been this happy in along time.
她会过来和你一起住吗
Wil she come to live with you?
况这个还为时尚早
Its too early to say.
但会的 可能会的
But yes, maybe yes.
我们该为孩子们着想
We have to think about the girls.
我想回那不勒斯住
| want to go back to live in Naples.
和尼诺吗 对
With Nino? YeS.
但他还不知道这件事
But he doesn't know yet.
他离开他妻子了吗 是的
Has he left his wife? YeS.
他现在和一个同事住在学校附近
He's living with a colleague near the university.
跟学生一样吗
Like a Student?
我想尽快去那不勒斯
| want to go to Naples as soon as possible
给我和孩子们找间公寓
and find an apartment for me and the girls.
好吧
All right.
我有个新消息
| have Some news.
个很棒的消息
| 1 Wonderfu| news.
我准备给咱们找一个新的大房子
Im going to find a big, new house, just for us,
不仅有卧室 还有游戏房
with a room for playing and a room for sleeping.
你要去哪里找这个新房子
And where will you find this new house?
我和航得罗说过了
lve spoken to Pietro.
所以呢
What do you mean?
我马上回来
咱 be right back.
以前我出于需要 把孩子们留给你
Until now lve left the girls with you out of necessity
也是因为航得罗需要调整一下
and because Pietro needed to readjust,
但现在他有目己的生活了 事情融变
but now that he has a life of his own, things will change.
我也有稳定下来的权利
1 also have the right to some stability.
然后呢
And So?
我准备搬去那不勒斯
Im moving to Naples.
我要和我的文儿们一起住 不行 我不相信你
Ilive there with my daughters. No, 1 don't trust youl
什和 么意  三思
What does that mean?
我不放心把她们留给你
| dont trust you with them.
你只顾目己顾不上她们
You're too taken with yourself to take care of them.
这是由你来决定的吗
You dont get to decide.
我不想让我的孙广们 在那不勒斯那种地方长大
1dont want my granddaughters to grow up in a city like Naples.
你知道目己在说什么吗
Do you realize what you're Saying?
那是一个充满暴力 混乱的城市
Its a violent disorderly city，
你们总是很过分
you are always SO exCessive.
你们 是指谁
"You"? Who are you talking about?
你 你们
About you, about all of you.
你们家 你的妈妈
About your family about your mother，
还有你们那里的一切
about the Scenes you make.
你再出行时 要把女儿们留给你妈妈吗
Wilyou leave Dede and Elsa with your mother when you travel?
我想留给谁残留给谁 我不同意
川leave them with whoever1want. No wayl
我不允许入得和艾尔沙
| dont want Dede and Elsa to come into contact
和一些失控的人一起生活
with people who are out of control.
我曾以为 你是我一直很需要的那种妈妈
1thought you were the mother figure 1d always needed.
但我错了
| was wrong.
我妈妈比你好多了
My mother is better than you.
埃茉娜
Elena_.
你想先洗个澡吗
fyou'd like to take Shower，
圭多回来 我们一起吃个饭
then we eat when Guido gets home.
也好
All right.
我给你准备好了客房
1 prepared the guest room for you.
我和我女儿一起睡
1 sleep with the girls.
你的一个朋友打过很多次电话
Afriend of yours has been calling.
她为什么打到这来
Why did she call here?
可能她知道你偶尔会来
Maybe she knows you drop in every now and then.
者拉来电 081 226942
"Lila called. 081 226942"
这个放到这里 不 不是这儿的
This goes here. No.…
试试这个
放这里 没错
把这片放那里吧
把这个一并放在那
对 和其他的放在一起
该睡觉了
It's time for bed .
晚安 妈妈
Goodnight Mamma.
晚安
Goodnight.
晚安 爷爷 晚安 妈妈
Goodnight Grandpa. Goodnight Mamma.
=尖女， dandD
这两位漂亮的小姐叫什么名字呀
What are the names of these two pretty young ladies?
入
二
和爷想知道你
Grandpa wants to know your full name.
们的全名
第伪.义罗塔
Dede Airota .
还有谁姓艾罗塔呢
Airota |ike who?
区区
Like Papa.
还有了呢
And then?
妈妈叫什么名字
And whats Mamma's name?
埃莱娜.格雷科
Elena Grecao.
你们姓格亩科还是广罗塔
And is your name Greco or Airota?
义罗塔
Airota.
真棒
That's right.
晚安 至贝们
Goodnight my dears.
你和尼诺:萨拉托雷 最近怎么样
How's it going with Nino 0
这样做值得吗
Was itworth it?
他是个聪明的男人 明白目身目标所在
He's an intelligent man, he knows his stuff
但他不太稳定
but he's erratic
我不喜欢他最近写的那些东西
1dont like the things he's written recently.
毕竟找到目身的定位是一件很难的事
After all, its hard to find one's way
在意大利当前的危机混乱之中
amid the chaos of the crisis in ltaly,
尤其是像他那样野心勃勃的男人
especially for men like him who want to do things.
我得去加会儿班
Im going to work a bit.
但是每个人有不同的做法
But there's doing and doing.
院拉托雷的取明是没有根基的
Sarratore is an intelligence without traditions,
他喜欢取悦擎权者
he'd rather make a good impression on the powers that be
而不是为某种理想而理斗
than stand up for an idea.
诡的聪明是没有根基的 是什么意思
加让 does "Nino's an intelligence without traditions" mean?
他谁都不是
That he's a nobody.
对于一个谁也不是的人 渴届成为
And for people like that, becoming someone
这对他比任何事情都重要
is more important than anything else.
导致的结果是 萨拉托雷先生会是一个不可靠的人
Consequently Mr. Sarratore is unreliable.
我的职明也是没有根基的
Im also an intelligence without traditions.
你也是 所以的确
Yes, and in fact..
这话什和 么意 意思
What do you mean?
我将儿子托付给你 但是你却背产了他
| entrusted a Son to you and you treated him dishonestly.
如果你一直想要另外一个男人 那为什么当初要巡给他
fyou wanted another man why did you marry him?
我当时并不知道我想要另一个 你撒族
1didnt know 1wanted another. You're lying.
是的 我在撤诉
Yes, 1m lying，
为什么你要通我给出一个前后统一的解释
because you're forcing me to give a linear explanation.
然而连贯的解释几乎总是访言
And linear explanations are almost always lies.
你也对我襄过彼得罗的坏话
Youve said bad things about Pietro too.
芝人至你也文持我对抗役得罗 你当时说详了吗
Actually youve backed me up against him. Were you lying?
不 我从始至终都是站在你这边的
No, lve always been on your side，
但要遵守一个前提
but within a pact you needed to respect.
什么 全身心地陪伴你的丈夫和女儿
What was that? To stay with your husband, your girls.
但是事与愿违
But that's not how it went
现在这个前提没有了 一切都变了
The pact is broken and it all changes.
随你霸么做吧 阿售尔
Do as you please, Adele,
我是埃茉娜.格备科 我的女儿是我的女儿
| am Elena Greco and my daughters are mine.
我他妈才不在乎你们艾罗塔家
|dont give a damn about you Airotas.
现在能看出来你是埃茉娜 格雷科
lt shows that you're Elena Greco.
这一切都太明显了
It's all too evident
但这两个孩子也是我儿子的
But the girls are my son's daughters,
她们与我们共同生活了几乎两年
theyve been living with us for two years
我们绝不会让你融这样贤了她们
and we wont allow you to ruin them.
想想你的所作所为 会给孩子们造成的伤害
"Think of the harm youl do to your kids，”
我离开艾罗培家时 和痢拉曾对我这样说
Said Lila when | was leaving my family.
竹么做才是对我女儿不好 怎样才能好
But what was bad for my daughters, what was good for them?
我的不好 我的好 都体现在何处呢
And what was bad and good for me?
和垢样才能把好和不好融合在一起
How did it correspond or diverge
或者说分开呢
from what was bad and good for them?
你呢 你为了尼诺 抛和寞了一切你所拥有的
You're throwing away everything you are for Nino?
甚至不异以毁掉你的家庭为代价
You're ruining your family for him?
别这么做 莱农
Don't do it Lenu.
他会利用你 他会榨干你的血
He'l use you, he'l suck your blood
他会慢慢吞掉你生存的信念 然后将你弃之不顾
helltake away your will to live and then hel adon el
为什么你念这么多的书
Why did you study so much?
为什么我他妈会滔费目己的时间去设想
Why did 1waste my time imagining
你会蔡我过上幸福美满的生活
youd live a wonderful life for me, too?
我销了 你真是个昌痴
| was wrong, youre just an idiot.
这才去那不勒斯的旅程似乎极其漫长
The trip to Naples seemed extremely long.
随着列车行驶速度渐慢 缓缓开入城区
The more the train slowed down, gliding into the urban space,
更多的焦虑和疲乱侵点了我的身心
the more anxious exhaustion took hold of me.
曾经与我息息相关的那不勒斯
lt seemed the Naples | had ties to，
我正在回归的那不勒斯
that | was returning to，
已经完全被尼话取代了
was now reduced to Nino.
我们会做出什么样的决定
What decision would we make，
尤其是在我们彼此对当下的关系 丝槛没有头绪的情况下
Since we had no clue about a practical form of our relationship?
当我们一起住在那不勒斯 他会有什么反应
How would he react to the idea of us all living together in Naples?
我唯一感到明确的事情是 我的渴烹火烧火类
Alll knew was 1 was burning with desire
我已经等不及要再次见到他
and | couldnt wait to see him again.
你心中有个想法却一直没告诉我
You have athought youre not telling me.
不 这不是真的
No, its not true.
我想知道到搬是什么
| want to know what it js.
是个不能说的秘密吗 不是
ls it aforbidden thought? No.
那你为什么不敢看我呢
Then why wont you look at me?
为什么不看着我
Why wont you look at me?
我准备和我的女儿们一起搬到这里
Im ready to move here with my daughters.
我们会非常幸福 是的
Well be very happy.
我目己还有点儿积蓄 波得罗会在生活上给我和广儿一些帮助
| have alittle money, Pietro will help me with the girls，
而且我马上要签订我的新书合同了
and 1m about to sign the contract for the new book.
我想找一个光线充足 且能坐拥海景的大公寓
ld like to find a big apartment with of light and a view of the sea.
我始终很想念大海
lve 全1 missed the Seal.
我马上开始找合适的房子
川 start looking for a house at once.
我们会找到的
We find 放.
一定是些态烦事 我去看看
Itll be some pain in the neck, | go see.
Hello?
我能晚点再打给你吗
Can 1 call you back later?
我和你这什么来着 这些大学里的及烦事儿
What did 1say? A pain in the neck from the university.
我还记告诉你 莉拉给我打过电话
1forgot to tell you Lila called me.
她坚持要联系上你
She insists you get in touch,
她还继续打电话 甚至打到挨利奥诺拉家
She's been calling continuously, even to Eleonora'S.
最后我不得不叫她消停会儿 我见到了她 然后和她说了
In the end | met with her and told her to give it a rest.
你见到她了
You met with her?
对 我和她还有卡门一起 简单喝了杯咖啡
1 grabbed a coffee with her and Carmen.
你二么没跟我说
Why didn't you tell me?
因为我不想让你担心 她俩真是一团乱
1didnt want to upset you, those two are messed up.
我只能况 她一直在问关于你的问题
Lila only asked questions about you:
她想台站你的穿着打扮 你有没有换友型
how you dress, youve changed your hairstyle,
你在公众场合友言是什么样子的
how you are when you 0下 in public.
而另一个快疯的女人 坚持想让你和加利亚尼女士谈一谈
That other Ilunatic wants you to speak to Mrs. Galliani，
因为娜迪亚正捧在法国避难
because Nadia has taken refuge in France
她想知道 是否有她哥哥由斯卡某的消息
and maybe she has news of her brother Pasquale.
你从来没什么空采时间 那是时候抽出空来了
You never have a free moment yet you found the time.…
你是在吧她俩的酷吗
Are you jealous of those two?
不 开个玩舌
No, |m joking.
今天真是烦人
Only pains in the neck today.
你好
Hello?
我跟你说过现在在忙
| told you 1m busy right now.
我们晚点讨论
We儿ldiscuss it later
我始终在逃避给玫拉打电话 告诉她
| avoided calling Lila to tell her about my decision
我回那不勒斯生活的决定
to move back to Naples.
我不希翌她掺和进我的事情中
1didnt want her getting mixed up in my affairs.
但我给卡门打了电话
Instead | called Carmen
她约我在一家市中心的餐吧见面
who agreed to meet me at a bar in the center.
卡门 菜农
Carmen .Lenu .
真好 终于见面了
How nice, at |astl
近来如何
How are things?
天哪 你真漂腕
My goodness, you're so beautifu|.
你气色真好
And you look so well
况哪儿的话 我总是很匆忙 甚至忽略了目己
No, 1m always rushing, | neglect myself.
你看起来气色挺好
U look wel|.
我可不这么认为
No, | don'.
我总是很担心
| have so many worries.
我们先点咖啡 袋后你跟我说说
Let's have coffee and you can tell me about it.
我不能符太久 但是我们很快融会再见面
| cant stay long, but we'l see each other soon.
要两杯咖啡 谢谢
Two coffees, please.
怎么了 你很快融要走吗
You're leaving So soon?
我和尼诺要去看看役得拉克路的公寓
Im going to see an apartment in Via Petrarca with Nino.
等等吧 晚点莉拉也要来
Wait Lila will be here soon.
还有者拉吗
Lila?
我以为这是你我之间的事情
1thought it was just you and me.
我喝了咖啡 然后真得走了 下次约吧
|上川 have coffee then 1 really must go. Let's do it another time.
者拉帮了我很多
Lila's helping me a lot.
她愿意为由斯卡荣做任何事情
She'd do anything for Pasquale.
lts not fair that the rich always win.
只有像我们这样的穷人才要付出代价 是的
Only poor people like us have to pay.
者拉乐于助人 关心朋友和家人
Lila helps everyone, She worries about her friends, her family.
甚至是斯特凡详
Even about Stefano
她帮安东尼找了一个房子 还和他德国的老婆成了朋友
She helped Antonio find a house and made friends with his German wife.
卡门 你跟我说说 我该如何帮你 因为等一下我融得走
Explain to me how | can help you,'cause | really gotta run.
你和那个教授聊聊吧 娜迪亚的母杀
Speak to the teacher Nadia's mother.
我敢肯定 她知道我哥哥的消息
lm sure she knows something about my brother.
好 我明天给她打电话
Allright 咱call her tomorrow.
不 你没明日
You dont get 比
不要给她打电话 电话里她什么都不会说的
dont call her on the phone, on the phone she wont tell you anything.
好 我去和她见个面
Allright 川| go and see her.
咖啡记我账上 再等等吧
Coffee's on me. Wait a bit longer.
者拉有非单重要的事情跟你说
Lila has something important to tell you.
你跟我襄吧
You tel| me.
我没有权利这么做
Its not my place.
你现在下定决心了吗
So, youve finally made up your mind?
确定要回那不勒斯了吗
Are you moving back to Naples?
是的
YeS.
你还和他在一起吗
You Still with him?
者拉 我爱尼详
Lila, 1 Ilove Nino
他也爱我
and he |oves me.
如果不是为了他 我长至不会写这本书
上fithadnt been for him 1wouldnt have written 司 book
我当时什么都做不了
| couldnt do it anymore.
他给了我力量重新开始
He gave me the strength to start over.
所以你要回这儿生活了
So you're coming back to live here.
你告诉卡门却不告诉我
You tel| Carmen and not me?
我本该告诉你的
| would have told you.
尔父母知道吗
Do your parents know?
埃莉沙也不知道吗 是的
Not even Elisa? Na
你妈妈不太好
Your mother isn'tt wel||.
她特么了
Whats wrong?
咳嗽 但是她不去看医生
A cough, but she won't go to the doctor.
我知道
| know.
卡门这你有重要的事情要和我说
Carmen says you have Something important to tell me.
不是一个好消息
Its not something pleasant.
说来听听
Let's hear 放.
我让安东尼奥帮信跟踪尼诸
| asked Antonio as a favor to follow Ninao.
什么意思
In what SenSse?
看着他都在做什么 为什么
To see what he does. Why?
为了你好 我能管好我目己
Foryour Sake. take care of myself.
你生气了
You're offended,
但你错了
but you're wrong.
我比你更了解尼诸
| know Nino better than you,
这融是我为什么要安乐尼奥跟踪他
that's why 1 asked Antonio to follow him.
我没生气
Im not offended,
不过你得说快点儿
but hurry up.
尼诺从来没有离开过他的妻子
Nino _ never |eft_ his Wife.
他们还生活在一起
He's still living with her.
加在这几天 他裤任命为
Theyve just made him a director
银行一个研究所的负责人
of an important bank research institute
融在他岳父手底下干活
under the patronage of his father-in-law.
伍么了
Whats wrong?
你已经知道了吗
You knew?
如果你不相信的话 我们可以去找他
f you don't believe me, go see him，
我可以当着他的面 一字一名重复刚才的话
川 repeat it to his face, word by word
残像我对你说的这样
like |just told you.
我相信你
| believe you.
如果你们要去 那我也一起
fyou go, |m coming too.
我们可以好好修理他
Wellfx him up good.
让他认栽
We cut off his cock
Im
S
Orry
，
我真的该走了
but now | really have to go.
再见 卡门 再见 莉拉
Bye, Carmen. Bye, Lila.